

# AKHIL PS Software Engineer

Tel: +91 7907155998 | Email: akhilpsinbox@gmail.com | Location: Kochi, India

Gender: Male | DOB: 29/04/1998

(A) https://bit.ly/akhilps in https://www.linkedin.com/in/akhil-ps https://github.com/akhilpsin



# **About Me**

I am a Software Engineer with 4 years of experience in Python script development. I excel in creating web automation scripts, OCR tools, data extractors. I have contributed to web applications using Flask, Django, and React, and worked with agile and waterfall project management models. My experience includes converting VB script macros and RPA processes to Python, as well as Excel operations and data management with MongoDB, SQL, and Azure. I am passionate about learning new technologies and enjoy coding.

# **Experience**

## Optum Global Solutions (India) Pvt. Ltd | Hyderabad, India

Digital health technology company captive of UHG that provides health care technology and business services

### **Senior Software Engineer**

[ 27/01/2023 - Present ]

- Developed a Python automation tool to streamline data extraction, cleaning, and structuring from multiple emulators, reducing manual effort by 80%. Controlled multiple macros in parallel and loaded cleaned data into an SQL database for auditor access via a web application.
- Implemented ETL processes for various business needs, including database cleaning, data structuring for web tools etc. Created Python scripts for generating comparative reports using live APIs and advanced data processing.
- · Built web solutions with Selenium, created VBScript macros for claims processing and auditing. Developed Python GUI tools to aid in macro conversion, enhancing productivity. Designed web apps with React and created APIs with Flask.

#### Guidehouse India Pvt. Ltd | Thiruvananthapuram, India

Global consulting firm that helps businesses and government entities solve complex challenges capabilities in management, technology, and risk consulting.

#### **Python Developer**

[16/02/2022 - 13/01/2023]

 Reporting, Automation, and Training: Produced and verified management reports with advanced Excel. Authored shell scripts for routine system tasks to boost efficiency, conducted trainings for new and existing staff in Python, designed detailed surveys with Qualtrics, and managed data within Salesforce.

#### **Associate**

[24/08/2020 - 15/02/2022]

- Cross-trained in Python, R, Spotfire, SQL, .NET C#, Automation Anywhere (RPA), Marvel design platform, and Excel during my training period.
- · As an associate in the data management team, I developed Python scripts for data extraction and cleaning, supported web application and ETL projects, assisted with Salesforce data loading and testing to ensure accuracy, created Qualtrics forms, and automated various Excel MIS tasks, boosting productivity and reducing manual effort.

## Skills

#### **Programming Languages**

Python, VB Scripting, SQL / NoSQL

### **Web Development Frameworks**

React, Flask, Django

#### **Cloud Platforms**

Azure

# **Version Control**

Git, Bitbucket

# **Software Proficiency**

• Microsoft Word, Excel, Power Point, Power BI

#### Robotic Process Automation (RPA)

UI Path, Power Automate

### **Python Libraries and Data Science Tools**

• Pandas, NumPy, Matplotlib, Scikit-learn, Polars, pytesseract, OpenCV, pdfplumber, pypdf, PyMuPDF, pywin32, Scrapy, BeautifulSoup, Requests, Selenium, Playwright

# **Education**

### Bachelor of Technology in Computer Science and Engineering

[ 2016 - 2020 ]

APJ Abdul Kalam Technological University | Kerala, India Percentage/CGPA: 7.64 CGPA

# Certifications

- Microsoft Azure AZ-900 : Microsoft Azure Fundamentals
- Data Analysis with Python by IBM on Coursera
- Microsoft Azure Machine Learning by Microsoft on Coursera.
- Architecting with Google Compute Engine by Google Cloud on Coursera
- Introduction to Git and GitHub by Google on Coursera.
- Agile Project Management by Google on Coursera.
- Agile with Atlassian Jira by Atlassian on Coursera.

# **Scholarly works**

**Published an journal in IJCRT**, analyzing the technical details and potential impact of academic medical web app project. (Link: https://ijcrt.org/papers/IJCRT2005507.pdf)

# Language

• English: advanced (B2)

• German: Beginner (A1/A2)

• Malayalam : Mother tongue

# **Hobies**

Workout

• Backpacking

Pencil sketch

Dance